we said we need a Rob in order to have
precise exceptions and also to be able
to easily recover from Branch
mispredictions so let's see how that
happens suppose we have a program that
reaches a branch and suppose that our
prediction was that the program will
continue here and fetch these three
instructions although in fact the
program branches so these three
instructions will be executed in a
branch misprediction let's say what
happens in this program in our Rob and
the registers first we will issue the
load here its output is the R1 so at the
beginning of all of this the Rob is
empty the issue and commit Point are the
same and that let's say that there are
no
instructions at the beginning of all of
this let's say that there are no
instructions so the rat is just pointing
to the registers and the issue and
commit point in the Rob are the same
meaning that the Rob is empty all of the
entries are free now let's see what
happens when we issue the load we move
the issue pointer here here the load
produces
R1 and R1 here in the rat is made to
point to the Rob one entry when we issue
the branch it produces no
output and thus we don't need to rename
anything and our issue pointer moves
here next what happens we will issue
instructions that shouldn't have been
issued but the processor doesn't know
that yet so it's just going to do it
anyway so this side here writes to
R2 and it gets the next Rob entry here
so the R2 entry is going to point to Rob
three and then this multiply
here is going to write to R3 and thus R3
is going to point to Rob four and then
the Divide is going to again write to R2
and that means that the entry for R2 in
the red will be changed from pointing to
the add to pointing to the Divide which
is Rob five and of course after all of
this issuing is done our issue pointer
is now here and we have five
instructions in our Rob now suppose that
this load takes a long time to produce a
value for example because it's a cash M
this Branch depends on the load so it
cannot complete until the load is done
and this add also depends on the load
and it cannot complete until the load is
done but this multiply here can begin
because R3 and R4 are not produced by
any of these instructions so this multip
might produce a value for example 15 and
originally it would write it to the
registers and at that point after the
branch misprediction but this multiply
can compute its value because R3 and R4
might be ready they're not produced by
any of the previous
instructions so the value of 15 when the
multiply
finishes would have been written to the
registers and then we don't know how to
undo the multiplication once we discover
that the branch has been mispredicted in
a raw based
processor the result of the
multiplication goes into its Rob entry
and its marked is done once this
multiply produces a value The Divide can
begin and let's say that the Divide is
producing a value of two and it might
also be done before the load returns so
now we have a situation where these two
instructions would have updated
registers and done permanent damage but
in a raw based processor all they did is
update the robw
entries the registers are still
unmodified